Three times nine is 27 . Four times nine is 36 .
Come in , please .
Here we are , Mary .
I have a most painful matter to discuss with you , Mary .
Your sister .
Have you heard from her lately ?
No , Mrs. Lowood . She doesn 't write often .
Have you any other relatives , Mary ?
No . Jacqueline brought me up .
Somehow , I never felt I needed other relatives .
That makes it all the more difficult .
Difficult ?
Has anything happened to Jacqueline ?
We don 't know , Mary .
We 've been unable to get in touch with your sister .
Sometimes she can be quite careless .
Why don 't you try Mrs. Redi ?
I have written repeatedly to Mrs. Redi .
She vouchsafes no information whatsoever .
It is six months , Mary , since your tuition has been paid .
Naturally , it 's impossible for you to stay on here as a paying pupil .
Course .
Miss Gilcrist and I have talked the matter over .
You can stay on here and work
with the younger children
as sort of an assistant teacher .
But , Mrs. Lowood , I can 't just stay on here
without knowing what 's happened to my sister .
Maybe if I went to New York ... If I saw Mrs. Redi myself - -
I doubt if you 'll get anything out of that woman .
But if you 'd like to try ,
I 'll advance you the money to make the trip to New York .
Of course , my dear , if you don 't find your sister ,
you can always come back here .
Thank you .
Mary .
Don 't come back .
No matter if you never find your sister ,
no matter what happens to you , don 't come back .
My parents died when I was a pupil .
I left , as you are leaving , but I didn 't have courage .
One must have courage to really live in the world .
I came back .
Gilcrist !
Agnes !
John Quincy Adams did not follow John Adams as president .
Build thee more stately mansions , O my soul ,
As the swift seasons roll ! Leave thy low-vaulted past !
Let each new temple , nobler than the last ,
Shut thee from heaven with a dome more vast ,
Tilt thou at length art free ...
That 's enough .
It seems all right , Joseph .
You see , we do keep up the quality of La Sagesse products ,
in spite of Jacqueline 's absence .
But you must know someone who has seen or heard of my sister .
I 'm afraid not .
Your sister had many friends , but they were not my friends .
I was only the manager of her plant .
Mrs. Redi , there 's one thing .
With Jacqueline gone , how do you carry on the business ?
What do you do with the receipts ?
How do you sign the checks ?
Why , Mary , I 'm amazed .
Didn 't Jacqueline tell you ?
She sold the business to me at least eight months ago .
It 's my business now .
I didn 't know that .
Yes , and I must say I 've done quite well with it .
Perhaps even better than Jacqueline .
There 's nothing you can think of ? Old letters ?
Anything that might give me some hint as to where I might find Jacqueline ?
Leave me your address . If I find anything , I 'll get in touch with you .
I 'm stopping at the Chatsworth .
Thank you , my dear .
Why , Mary !
- Hello , Frances . - How are you , honey ?
How 's Miss Jacqueline ?
I don 't know . That 's why I came to see Mrs. Redi .
I 'm trying to find her .
You mean she 's gone , and you don 't know where she is ?
Come here a minute .
I don 't get this .
Miss Jacqueline 's so crazy about you .
She was always talking about you ,
and she had your picture in her office , and ...
I know .
For the first time , I 'm beginning to feel frightened .
I almost feel as if I 'd never known my sister .
Nothing 's happened to her .
It 's just that I can 't understand her not keeping in touch with you .
I can 't understand it at all .
Well , don 't worry about it .
I saw Miss Jacqueline myself about a week ago
at a restaurant the boyfriend took me to .
A little Italian place down in the Village called the Dante .
- The Dante ? - Yes , it 's on Perry Street .
Why don 't you ask the people who own the place ?
They 'll remember Miss Jacqueline .
Anybody who ever sees her never forgets her .
I 'll try there .
I 'm sorry to bother you . I want to ask you about my sister .
- Yes ? - I thought you might know her .
She was seen here about a week ago .
Her name is Jacqueline Gibson .
I don 't know no Gibson . This is a restaurant .
Many people come here .
She 's very beautiful .
I wish I could tell you what she looks like .
I 'm sure you 'd remember her .
She 's tall , with dark hair .
Once you 'd seen my sister , you 'd never forget her .
Giacomo , la bellissima madonna .
Maybe .
Let me look at you .
Why , you could be her sister .
Yes . Yes , if she made that much impression on you ,
I 'm sure it was Jacqueline .
She hasn 't been here for a long time .
- But she was here . - Oh , yes , yes .
One day a beautiful car comes here .
This beautiful woman in furs gets out .
There is a handsome man with her and the chauffeur .
The lady rents one of our upstairs rooms ,
and the chauffeur changes the lock on the doors .
Then the lady does not come back .
Not to live , anyhow .
She came back three or four times ,
but always alone .
Just to eat .
You mean she just came here ,
rented the room , locked it and left ?
Yes . And pays the rent every month .
Could you let me see that room ?
If it is hers , there might be something there
to help me find my sister .
No . The rent is paid . The lady asked us to promise .
I won 't open the door .
Please .
It 's important .
What did he say ?
He said he always wanted to see the inside of this room anyway .
I tell you , young lady , when a thing like this comes up ,
you 've got to go to the police .
What do you think people pay taxes for ?
It ain 't just to keep us chasing after crooks
and regulating traffic .
We 're supposed to help everybody .
Now , you 've got to go to the police about your sister , miss .
Uh , I 've had some experience with the Bureau of Missing Persons - -
Yeah . Well , Mr. Hoag ,
lost persons are the concern of the Missing Persons Bureau .
You stick to your poetry .
You 're the poet , Jason .
Well , in a way , that makes everything my business , doesn 't it ?
Were you going to make a suggestion ?
Yes .
I was going to ask you to look into your own heart .
Do you really want to find your sister ?
Oh , my Jason , always laughing ,
always joking to help others .
He 's a good boy , miss . He just talks that way .
I 'm a good boy , but no one listens to what I say .
Now , you do what I tell you , young lady ,
and go to the Missing Persons Bureau for your sister .
- If you 'll give me the address . - Certainly .
- She was only 16 , and she seemed - - - Had she ever run away before ?
What did he have on when last seen ?
He went out without his hat or his coat .
It 's very cold for such an old man .
Any identifying marks or characteristics ?
Scars , amputation , tattoo marks , speech impediments ?
No , none .
- Sign here . - Any further details ?
Oh , she sold her business about eight months ago
to Mrs. Esther Redi .
What relation are you to the missing person ?
Sister .
Sign here .
Excuse me , uh , I 'm Irving August , private investigator .
I think I can help you . Here 's my card .
The name may not mean anything to you , but just say the word ,
and I 'll have your sister for you in 48 hours .
Can you ?
Look , sister , Manhattan is only nine miles long
and four and a half miles wide .
I ain 't never been off it .
I know it like ... Like you know your own backyard .
Now , you just get me a small retainer , say , uh , 50 bucks ,
and I get your sister for you . I guarantee it .
I haven 't any money right now , but I 'll get a job and - -
Lady , this kind of work costs money .
I gotta cover all the hospitals , the morgue .
That 's the first place you gotta go , and it ain 't pleasant , the morgue .
You know who I am , August ?
Sure , I do .
Then you know if I give you a little advice , it 'll be good advice .
Yeah , sure .
That girl was looking for Jacqueline Gibson .
If I were you , I 'd forget it .
Okay , Mr. Radeau , it 's forgot .
Hey , Danny , get me the file on Jacqueline Gibson , will you ?
- Whom do you wish to see ? - Mr. Gregory Ward , please .
And what is it about , Miss Gibson ?
A personal matter . I was given Mr. Ward 's name .
May I ask who gave you his name ?
The morgue .
Do you feel all right ?
I feel like an idiot , fainting in a stranger 's office .
We 're not exactly strangers , Mary .
Jacqueline spoke about you often . I suppose she told you about me ?
No . At the morgue ,
they told me a Mr. Gregory Ward had made inquiries about Jacqueline .
At the morgue ? No wonder you fainted .
I wish you 'd come to me first .
Then you know where Jacqueline is ?
But I 'd give a great deal to know .
Why ?
I love your sister , Mary . I love her very much .
It 's easy to understand now , isn 't it ?
A man would look for her anywhere , Mary .
There 's something exciting and unforgettable about Jacqueline .
Something you never quite get hold of .
Something that keeps a man following after her .
Because I loved Jacqueline , I thought I knew her .
Today I found out such strange things .
Frightening things .
I saw a hangman 's noose that Jacqueline had hanging .
Waiting .
Well , at least I can explain that .
Your sister had a feeling about life .
That it wasn 't worth living unless one could end it .
- I helped her get that room . - Weren 't you afraid ?
Afraid she might commit suicide ?
People who commit suicide don 't talk about it .
No , that room made her happy
in some strange way I couldn 't understand .
She lived in a world of her own fancy .
She didn 't always tell the truth .
In fact , I 'm afraid she didn 't know what the truth was .
It 's difficult to explain to a youngster .
I 'm not a youngster . I can understand .
Oh . The color 's returning to your cheeks .
You look as if you were coming back to life .
Are you sure you didn 't faint because you were hungry ?
You know , I didn 't have lunch .
Well , it 's nearly 6 . Time for dinner .
Thank you . It was a lovely dinner .
- Good . - But I feel guilty .
It doesn 't seem right for me to enjoy myself
with Jacqueline gone .
Look here , you can 't make looking for Jacqueline your life 's work .
You 've got to do other things . Live .
Get some enjoyment out of life .
I hope you 'll let me help you .
Thank you . Good night .
Good night , Mary .
Miss Gibson , I 've been waiting for you .
I want you to know I decided to take your case .
- Mr. August , I 'm not at all sure - - - Look , don 't say a word .
I 've taken an interest in you ,
and I 'm willing to put up my time to help you .
Besides , I think I know where to find your sister .
- Where ? - Wait a minute .
This has got a lot of angles .
You gotta take it easy . Tell me , do you know 3 Mrs. Redi ?
Well , yeah . She bought my sister 's business .
That 's what she told you .
I looked it up in the Hall of Records .
Your sister deeded her the business as an outright gift .
Why would Mrs. Redi lie to me ?
That 's what I tried to find out .
I went to the La Sagesse .
Used a phony health inspector 's badge .
They let me go through the works .
All but one room . That room was locked .
I 'd like to see the inside of that room .
You think my sister is there ?
- Can 't tell . - Can we go there now ?
Sister , you can 't just go breaking into places .
They got a night watchman and locks on their door .
If my sister 's in that room ,
it won 't make any difference about warrants and things .
- I want to go there . - I don 't know if ...
If I wanna go with you or not .
Which room is it ?
It 's the last door at the end of this hall .
- You scared ? - Yes .
- Let 's - - Let 's get out of here . - No .
You could go on , Mr. August . You could open the door .
I 'd stay right here .
It 's only a little way , Mr. August .
We can 't stand here all night .
You could go and open the door .
Mr. August . The night watchman .
The night watchman . He 's in the salon .
Mr. August . What is it ?
What 's the matter ?
Mr. August .
Do you know where you 're going , lady ?
You 've been to the end of the line and back again .
I hope you enjoyed the ride .
Please . Please .
I want your help , please .
- Those men , don 't let them get out . - What 's the matter now ?
- One of them has been murdered . - Murdered ?
What men ?
But they were there .
Oh , yeah ?
Extra ! Murder , read all about it !
Thank you .
It 's about another murder . A woman on 52nd Street .
But you do believe me ?
Well , the important thing is the police won 't believe you .
I saw him on the floor .
He was cut ... here .
The blood was running out .
He was dead . I know it .
And then on the subway , I saw him .
White ... with the men holding him up between them .
Yes , of course .
But the police would say you 'd probably had a bad dream .
He was a kind little man , in his way .
And I made him go down that hall into the darkness .
I made him do it .
Drink your milk .
I don 't like to be ordered to do anything .
I 'm sorry .
I didn 't intend to treat you like a child .
But you have treated me that way .
I won 't do it again . We 're friends .
I promise I 'll never order you about again .
However , I won 't say that I 'll not take charge occasionally ,
and I 'm going to take charge right now .
- I have a job for you . - A job ?
Mm-hm . Remember you told me you were pretty good with youngsters ?
Today I bumped into an old friend of mine , 3 Mrs. Wheeler .
She runs a settlement house down in the Village ,
and she 's looking for a kindergarten teacher .
Why , I 'd like that .
It 's not much money , but it 'd be enough to live on .
You 'd have to move out of that hotel and into a furnished room .
Maybe the Romaris would have a room . They seem nice .
- The people at the restaurant ? - Yes .
If you want , I have time to take you to see Mrs. Wheeler right now .
Yes , sir .
Mr. Ward will see you in just a few minutes .
- Won 't you wait , Dr. Judd ? - Thank you .
Uh , Dr. Judd ?
- Are you Dr. Louis Judd ? - Yes .
I read your book , the one in which you wrote about the cure for drinking .
You 're not a dipsomaniac at your age ?
No , it 's ... It 's my father . I ...
I wanted to talk to you .
You wrote about cures .
I 'm sorry , I don 't practice anymore .
I find it easier to write about mental illness
and , uh , leave the cure of it to others .
Yes , sir .
Mr. Ward is free now , doctor .
There are any number of other psychiatrists
who can help your father .
Dipsomania is rather sordid .
Thank you .
I 've come from Jacqueline . She needs money .
I thought you told me you didn 't know where she was .
I didn 't . She came to me a few days ago .
To put it delicately ,
her care imposes a financial burden upon me .
She thought you might lighten that burden .
If Jacqueline wants money from me , she can come to me herself .
I 'm afraid she can 't do that , Ward .
- It would endanger her . - This is nonsense .
Unless I know where Jacqueline is and how she is ,
I 'm not going to give you any money .
You 're a curious man .
You 're willing to jeopardize Jacqueline 's life
in order to satisfy your own curiosity .
It 's not just for myself I 'm asking .
Her sister 's here . The kid 's half crazy with anxiety .
As a man , you distrust me .
Perhaps you can believe me as a physician .
Well , then I can tell you that in addition to other dangers ,
there 's a grave danger of Jacqueline losing her sanity .
I would advise against you seeing her .
But why ?
She 's been ill , erratic , but I 've never known of anything like that .
You can believe me or not , just as you choose .
- How much does she want ? - She can use a hundred dollars .
- I 'll give you a check . - She can only use cash .
I haven 't got that much in cash .
How much have you ?
About $ 45 .
For the time being , I imagine that must do .
Thank you .
Tell me , how is Jacqueline ?
- Oh , as beautiful as ever . - Tell me .
She 's nervous , naturally , in the circumstances .
What circumstances ?
Mama , see ? Miss Gibson helped me .
It 's a table .
Beautiful ! We show it to Papa tonight .
Did Michele eat her soup today ?
She 's been an angel .
Mommy , wait for me .
Angelo , wait !
Well , Mary , aren 't you the popular one . You 've a visitor again .
- Mr. Ward ? - No , not this time .
It 's a gentleman called Judd .
Dr. Judd .
Dr. Judd ?
Yes , Miss Gibson . I 've come to take you to your sister .
Don 't be so amazed . It 's a very ordinary matter .
I 'm Jacqueline 's physician . Mr. Ward told me you were in town ,
and Jacqueline sent me to bring you to her .
Then you know where she is ?
If I didn 't know where she was , could I take you to her ?
Get your hat and coat . We haven 't much time .
It 's amid marble splendors such as these
that Jacqueline dwells .
One can take either staircase .
I prefer the left , the sinister side .
She 's not here . She 's gone .
I don 't know why she left .
She knows she shouldn 't have .
She 's left me to meet them alone .
I can 't .
What makes you so nervous , Dr. Judd ?
- Who are they ? - I can 't stay here .
I 'll have to leave you .
Jacqueline !
Is this her ?
No .
- Where 's Jacqueline Gibson ? - I don 't know .
- She was just here . Where 'd she go ? - I tell you , I don 't know .
That 's funny , you went out with her and came back alone
- and don 't know where she went ? - I don 't know .
Why do you want Jacqueline ?
What right have you to question me ?
I have all the right in the world .
I 'm Paul Radeau , a private investigator ,
and I 've been hired to find your sister by her husband ,
Gregory Ward .
Husband .
Say , what are you thinking of , Bella ? Can I eat dry ?
Oh , the wine . I have forgotten the wine .
Look , Mary , just because I kept a secret from you
doesn 't make a monster of me .
Please . I can 't go on explaining things like this
to your right ear .
Last night in this very restaurant ,
Mr. Jason Hoag paid a very pretty compliment to my right ear .
- Who the devil is he ? - A poet .
He 's sitting right over there .
That 's his table , the one at the feet of Dante .
Do you remember the first day you came to my office ,
frightened and broken up ,
and I asked you if Jacqueline had ever spoken about me to you ?
You said no .
Well , then how could I tell you we were married ?
And afterwards ... Well , I didn 't tell you afterwards
because there were so many things coming up
to make me worry and wonder ...
Ah , my beautiful one .
Why do you bring me wine , when you yourself are so intoxicating ?
You 're my favorite audience , Bella .
Why can 't everyone be happy like we are ?
Laugh and have a good time .
That poor little one .
So sad because she can 't find her sister .
And that man with her , he doesn 't make her laugh .
Just sits and talks .
We are happy , Mrs. Romari , because you have everything ,
and I have nothing to lose .
Why , you should make her laugh , Jason .
Come , make jokes for her .
You could have told me anytime you were Jacqueline 's husband .
Things change , Mary .
The reasons for finding Jacqueline changed .
I want to find her to settle things .
What things ? Why ?
Why you two are so sad ?
Your food will not digest , and your wine will sour .
You must laugh to eat well .
I 've brought Jason to make you laugh .
Um , Mr. Hoag , this is Mr. Ward .
Sit down . I 'll get the rest of your dinner .
I 'm under orders to make you laugh .
In Mrs. Romari 's mind ,
poetry and humor have some strange affinity ,
which they don 't have in fact .
She wants me to play the fool for you ,
but ... suddenly , Miss Gibson , I feel as sad as you do .
Well , then , I 've spoiled your dinner .
You food won 't digest , and your wine will sour .
You 'll have to make all the jokes
because I 'm going to be serious .
I 'm going to find your sister .
Shuffle the cards well , Natalie .
This is a trick of telepathy , not card manipulation .
Now pass the cards to me .
Gladys , will you hand the cards to Louis while I answer the door ?
Jason ! How nice to see you .
I 've brought some friends , Natalie .
- May we come to your party ? - Oh , of course . Come in .
Now , all of you must remember the cards that you have selected ...
- Mrs. Cortez , Mary Gibson and Mr. Ward . - So nice to meet you .
The cards can 't speak for themselves .
- It 's purely a matter of the mind . - You 'll have to excuse me .
Mrs. Freeman , yours was the jack of spades .
Gladys , seven of diamonds .
Yours , Mrs. Gosden , the queen of hearts .
How do you ever do it , Louis ?
Hello , Jason .
Where 's Jacqueline Gibson ?
- What a peculiar question . - I saw you with her last week .
I knew you 'd be here tonight . Where is she ?
My dear fellow , it 's neither your business to ask , nor mine to tell .
Oh , wait .
Look over there .
Do you see that girl ? That 's Jacqueline 's sister .
It 's because of her that I ask .
But why come to me ?
Because there was another girl , years ago .
A nice girl .
She lived in Barrow Street .
I saw her with you once .
I saw her with you twice .
And then I never saw her again .
She was my patient .
What was she to you ?
I don 't think you 'd understand if I told you .
I think I understand without your telling me .
I know something of your history , Jason .
I know you haven 't written for ten years .
I 've lost the knack .
After that wonderful first book ?
After all the adulation and good reviews ?
I 'd have given anything to have written that book .
You had all my admiration and respect ... once .
There you are . Do you know any more card tricks ?
Hello , Ward .
My dear Miss Gibson .
Gibson ?
Are you Jacqueline 's sister ?
- Yes . Do you - - ? - Know her ?
Oh , my dear , we were intimate .
The times we used to have together .
I 'll bet she never told you about that . You 're too young .
I 'm afraid you don 't understand . Miss Gibson 's sister is missing .
Missing ? Well , no wonder .
When she took up with Louis Judd ,
she went out of circulation just like that .
My dear , have I said something ?
Too many people here .
Perhaps Jacqueline is lonely for me .
You see , Mary , I 'm not quite a fool .
At least you knew about Dr. Judd .
Yes .
And you knew he 'd be here .
And now that I 've shown you that I know that much ,
and can guess more , will you trust me to look for Jacqueline ?
I want you to look for Jacqueline .
I 'm a terrible failure , Mary .
A book clerk by day and a poet by night .
Not a very good one .
But if you 'll trust me , at this one thing , I won 't fail .
I 'll find your sister .
You have such lovely hands , Miss Gottschalk .
So slim and capable .
Mr. Hoag , I really shouldn 't be doing this , you know .
It 's against the rules . Why did you say you wanted them ?
I 'd like to see what kind of books my friends read
so I 'll know what to buy them as presents .
Nothing nicer than a book for a gift .
Hmm .
Who was the first one ? Mrs. Redi ?
- Mm-hm . - P , Q , R ...
Yes . Here it is .
- And the other was Judd ? - Yes , Dr. Louis Judd .
Mm-hm . He 's here too .
Would it be asking too much , Miss Gottschalk ,
for you to get me these books ?
No , not at all , Mr. Hoag .
Why , Mr. Hoag ,
most of these books are on the closed shelf .
You 'll have to get permission .
I wouldn 't want to take them out . I 'd just like to look at them .
Well , since you 're over 21 .
Mimi .
Come in .
What is it ?
A parallelogram with a split triangle in its very center .
I found out that Mrs. Redi reads the same books as Dr. Judd .
Oh , I don 't think that 's so revealing .
But who is Judd ? A psychiatrist .
Now , it 's quite natural that he should read books
on the history of old religious societies .
But why should Mrs. Redi , a woman with a beauty parlor ?
- I don 't know . - That 's just it .
And this figure . She traced it .
The book I saw at the library had been marked " perfect "
by the library inspector in March .
Mrs. Redi had it out in April ,
and no one else had read it since .
This figure is the symbol of the Palladists .
It 's all clear to me now . So clear .
I thought it would be , but just to be sure ,
I 'll tell you that the Palladists are a society of devil worshipers .
Devil worshipers !
But , look , I 'm serious .
It 's a very real and earnest society .
- A dangerous society . - I can imagine .
Well , sometime before those nice white gloves are dry ,
you 're going to go and find out a few things about this Mrs. Redi .
Is Mrs. Redi nice to work for ?
Uh , Redi 's all right ,
but there 's only one Miss Jacqueline .
Mrs. Redi seems rather an odd woman to me .
She 's really a pretty good sort .
What does she do with herself after business hours ?
It 's always seemed to me that she was sort of lonely and unhappy .
Well , Mary , I guess most people are .
There . That 's it .
In the old days , this would have been on the house .
Aw , the tip is , anyhow .
Besides , I like to do your hair .
Thank you .
Do you know what this is , Frances ?
Why , I ought to .
It 's Mrs. Redi 's new trademark .
Of course . I should have known .
This figure 's been puzzling me .
Hello , Mary . It 's nice to see you .
- No news of Jacqueline ? - I 'm afraid not .
Well , that 's too bad .
What did she want ?
Nothing . I just did her hair .
What were you talking about ?
Nothing .
Nothing ? Why , that 's absurd .
I heard you laughing and talking . She was asking questions .
Oh , well , she was asking about you .
Whether it was nice to work for you or not .
And that was all ?
Well , she asked about the trademark .
- What did she want to know ? - She showed me a drawing .
Oh , you fool ! Why , that symbol is us .
Us !
She was asking about us !
- Mary - Yes ? -
This is Mrs. Redi , Mary .
Oh , I 'll be out in a minute .
That won 't be necessary .
I haven 't much to say .
If I were you , Mary , I 'd go back to school .
I 'd make no further attempt to find Jacqueline .
I can 't give up looking for her , Mrs. Redi ,
no matter what you 're hinting at .
I have no intention whatsoever of hinting .
Your sister , Mary , is a murderess .
She killed Irving August .
Stabbed him out of fright
when he discovered where she was hiding .
I don 't believe you .
I had to help get rid of the body .
You saw it on the subway .
And I warn you , Mary , go back .
You don 't know what you 're doing
or what dreadful things you might bring about
by looking for your sister .
You go back to school .
- I 'm sorry to be late , Natalie . - We haven 't begun tea yet .
- Hello , Frances . - Hello , Mrs. Redi .
- How do you do ? - Mrs. Redi .
Won 't you pour ?
I 'm sorry . I 'm nervous .
- This is very trying for me . - I know .
You introduced Jacqueline to us .
- But how could you tell ? - I should have known .
She had no sincerity , no real belief .
Miss Rowan , do you take cream ?
Please , Natalie , would you mind pouring ?
You shouldn 't be nervous .
There 's nothing personal or vengeful in what we are about to do .
We have only to make a decision .
But it can be such a horrible decision ,
because we 're all pledged to nonviolence .
Now , this - -
Our founder must have known
when he wrote these seemingly contradictory rules .
The rule of nonviolence
and the law that whoever betrays us must die .
He must have known .
But I don 't understand it .
Some of us , Frances , must believe without understanding .
Yes , I suppose so .
I went back through the history last night .
I read about Johann Rosenquartz .
- I read what he wrote about - - - I can quote it fully , Mrs. Redi .
" We will avoid violence . For , once undertaken ,
violence can become its own master
and lead to either good or evil . "
- But he also wrote that - - - I can quote that too .
" Those who go out into the marketplaces and let their tongues speak of us
and give knowledge of our being and our deeds ,
whomsoever doeth this shall die . "
I 'm puzzled .
Since our order was founded , six betrayals have been listed .
And six deaths as punishment .
- And now there 's Jacqueline . - Oh , but ...
But you can 't do anything to her .
- You mustn 't hurt her ! - But she betrayed us , Frances .
She didn 't betray us . She was only going to a doctor .
A psychiatrist .
She told him , Frances . She told him about us .
I know this is difficult for you .
- I know that you love her . - But she didn 't betray us !
Even if I believed that ,
I would still consider her a very dangerous woman .
There is the matter of Irving August 's death .
Without consulting me , Mrs. Redi was " I advised enough
to have the body removed by Leo and Durk .
This makes us all a party to the crime .
What if there 's a trial ?
What if Jacqueline is asked about the removal of the body ?
Do you think , Frances , that she would keep silent ?
It is a real danger and one which forces our decision .
- And Jacqueline 's sister ? - I 've taken care of Mary .
I 've spoken to her , and she 's going back to school .
Good . Then it is decided .
Leo and Durk and I will complete our plans .
Mary !
This is wonderful , your coming here so unexpectedly .
It 's almost like a wish come true .
I want to show you my room .
I want you to see all of it .
But it 's a small room , Jason .
It 's grown big with the years .
And my window , through which I see the world .
It 's beautiful .
That searchlight and the stars .
Oh , that 's not a searchlight .
It 's a sword blade cutting the blue cloak of a prince .
- Not stars - - - Jason .
I 'm going back to Highcliffe .
I 've come to say goodbye .
But I thought your coming up here to the third floor to see me ...
well , that it was your advent into my world .
Turns out to be goodbye . Why ?
Please don 't make me tell you , Jason .
I thought I was your friend , Mary .
Just " goodbye " isn 't enough for a friend .
I 'd begun to write again .
That 's what I was doing when you came in .
It 's because of Jacqueline .
I can 't go on looking for her .
You went to see Mrs. Redi .
She told you something . What was it ?
Jacqueline 's a murderess .
She killed a man .
You believe that ?
I have to . It was Irving August .
Everything Mrs. Redi said , it fits in with what I saw .
She even knew that I 'd seen his body on the subway .
But if it 's true , then there 's all the more reason
for you to find Jacqueline .
And Gregory , he loves her .
He loves you , Mary . You 'll have to tell him .
He 's Jacqueline 's husband . I can 't .
But you 've got to tell him , Mary .
Even if only for the practical reason that he 's a lawyer
and will know what to do .
I 'm going to phone him .
Well , she 's got to be found .
That 's the first step .
She 's got to be found so she can give herself up to the police .
But we 've tried so long to find her .
Judd could tell us , if he would .
- Do you think he knows about this ? - I don 't know .
Well , he 's clever .
And he 's cautious , in his way .
I think if he knew , he 'd advise her to do what I want .
Surrender herself to the police and stand trial .
- I don 't think he knows . - We could tell him .
- Could you find him ? - I suppose so .
I guess I could pick him up somewhere .
Jason . I sometimes wonder ...
You 're so sweet to me . So kind and sympathetic .
I don 't know how I can ever thank you .
Thank me ?
You don 't have to thank me .
What 's that ?
Verse . Verse I wrote .
Don 't bother going up .
I can do this all night , Jason . Watch .
Following me to find Jacqueline ?
- Mm-hm . - Well , it won 't work .
Love and understanding won 't make a good detective
out of a recalcitrant poet .
Actually , there are two favors I want to ask of you .
One as a poet , one as a detective .
Sounds strange . I 'm going to be very wary .
Some time ago , you spoke about my writing again .
I want your help .
I 'd like you to bring this to your publisher .
This is curious , Jason .
Half the time you talk as if Shakespeare weren 't fit to tie your Shoelaces .
Now this sudden humility .
I should like people to read what I have written .
I hope it 'll find as much favor as your other book .
But somehow I doubt it . The time is out of tune .
Why not let your publisher judge that ?
Wait . There 's that other favor .
I 'd forgotten .
Tell me where Jacqueline is . We 've got to find her .
You don 't really expect me to do that , do you ?
- Yes , when I tell you . - Tell me what ?
You 'll have good enough sense to tell us where she is
when I tell you she 's a murderess .
She killed a man .
Tell me , why this sudden desire to publish ?
To awaken like Byron and find yourself famous ?
- I think it 's time . - No other reason ?
No woman ? Not the little Miss Gibson ?
Perhaps .
Wait a minute . I 'll call her .
Jacqueline , this is Judd .
Jacqueline .
- Who is it ? - Judd . I 'm here with your sister .
Come on down .
Oh , Mary .
Jacqueline .
It 's all right .
You 're safe . Nothing 's going to hurt you .
Your husband seems very certain of that .
Yes . I 'm very certain there 's only one way to help you , Jacqueline .
To protect you .
You 've got to come with us .
Let me do all I can as a lawyer to straighten out Irving August 's death .
You must come with us , darling .
Let us help you .
For me , this seems to be the end of a delightful relationship .
Here , this will put some life into you .
It 's like coming back to life .
It would be much easier , Jacqueline , if you 'd tell me exactly what happened .
I 'd know what to do for you .
Please , Jacqueline .
You know about the Palladists .
You know who they are .
What they are .
I was one of them .
Jacqueline was always a sensationalist ,
trying to seize on to something ,
anything to bring her happiness .
Through Mrs. Redi , she stumbled onto the Palladist movement .
It appealed to her .
I wasn 't happy with them .
Wanted to break away .
I was miserable .
I went to Louis for help .
They felt that I 'd betrayed them .
They wanted me to die .
Kill myself .
They kept me locked up at La Sagesse .
I was there such a long time .
You can imagine the effect of such imprisonment on Jacqueline .
I was terrified .
Darkness in the corners of the room .
All the little noises .
Then one night , the door opened .
A man came in .
Tiptoeing in .
I had a scissors in my hand .
I struck at him .
Don 't . We know what happened . Don 't go on .
Any court in the land would understand .
We 'll wait a few days . Let you rest .
Then we 'll go to the police .
Why can 't Jacqueline stay here with me for a few days ?
You 'd like that , wouldn 't you ?
There 's my old friend .
- The searchlight ? - Mm-hm . Cyrano 's sword .
That 's a funny thing to call it .
I like it .
I 've always loved the story .
A man knowing he couldn 't have the woman he loved
and wooing her for his friend .
We 're friends , aren 't we , Gregory ?
It 's been a hard evening for both of you .
Perhaps you ought to take Jacqueline to your room , Mary .
Good night , Jacqueline .
- Good night , Mary . - Good night .
This is no time to play Cyrano .
What was in your mind ?
I wanted to get things clear for Jacqueline .
- To let her know . - To let her know what ?
That you love Mary .
She 'll have to know sometime .
Not from me .
And not from Mary .
Goodbye , darling . I 'll only be gone until 3 .
Goodbye .
If you get lonely , go down and see Mrs. Romari .
I told her you were staying with me .
I won 't be lonely .
♪ " When Will you pay me ? " ♪
♪ Say the bells of Old Bailey ♪
♪ " That I don 't know " ♪
♪ Says the great bell of Bow ♪
♪ Here comes a candle To light you to bed ♪
♪ Here comes a chopper To chop off your head ♪
Yes , this is Mary .
But she couldn 't have gone out .
No .
Are you sure it wasn 't Jason she went with , or Mr. Ward ?
Two men ?
No .
I 'll get home as soon as I can , Mr. Romari .
The acceptance of a secret is an obligation .
In this case , my dear , the obligation carried with it
the necessity of dying if one betrayed that secret .
You understand that , don 't you ?
Yes , I understand it .
Then you also understand that you must die .
No .
Jacqueline , you 've spoken so often of ending it all .
I can 't understand why this should be so difficult for you .
You have only to drink a little .
Yes , Jacqueline .
You were always talking suicide ,
of ending your life when you wanted to .
Yes .
When I wanted to .
It doesn 't matter .
You want to now . You should want to .
It is your obligation , your duty .
You have only to stretch out your hand ,
take up the glass and drink a little .
It won 't hurt .
No , no , no .
You have a strange kind of courage , Jason .
Perhaps you have enough courage
to hear what I have been keeping from you all these years .
That girl you loved , that other patient of mine ...
she didn 't disappear .
She 's in an asylum .
A horrible , raving thing .
I never wanted you to know .
And all the while ...
you 've been my friend .
Please , may I have a drink of water ?
I 'm very thirsty .
Drink .
No .
There will be no water and no rest . You may as we " drink .
No ! No !
If you like , I 'll go with you to dinner .
- I 'd like that . - Jason !
I can 't find Gregory .
I 've been trying to find him .
What 's wrong , Mary ?
Jacqueline . Mr. Romari phoned me .
She went out this afternoon with two men he 'd never seen before .
They may have been friends of hers .
No , she wouldn 't have gone with anyone unless she were compelled .
All these months of hiding have made her frightened of the streets and people .
- I wonder ... - What ?
They may have found her .
Would they hurt her ?
I don 't know .
You 'd better go up to your room and wait for us , Mary .
Go ahead , Jacqueline .
Go ahead .
It is late .
Drink it , Jacqueline !
There 's nothing else for you to do !
They say you 've got to die .
Drink it , Jacqueline ! You 've got to ! I can 't stand this !
No ! No , I can 't let you die !
The only time I was ever happy was when I was working with you .
You were always so good to me .
You may go now , Jacqueline . The decision was against violence .
But there 'll be another decision .
Today , tomorrow ... We 'll find you .
But now you may go .
I told you you could go .
Please help me . There 's a man following me .
I shouldn 't wonder , babe .
Please , I 'm serious . Help me .
I 'll help you to a beer and a sandwich .
Come along , babe . Come along .
Who are you ?
I 'm Mimi .
- I 'm dying . - No .
Yes . I 've been quiet .
Oh , ever so quiet .
I hardly move ,
and yet it keeps coming all the time ,
closer and closer .
And I rest and I rest and ... still I 'm dying .
And you don 't want to die .
I 've always wanted to die .
- Always . - I 'm afraid .
And I 'm tired of being afraid , of waiting .
- Why wait ? - I 'm not going to wait .
I 'm going out , and I 'm going to laugh and dance
and do all the things I used to do .
And then ?
I don 't know .
You will die .
Now that you 've hounded and worried her half to death ,
you don 't even know where she is .
At least tell me , has she been here ?
Yes .
She left here an hour ago .
She may even be home by now . Why don 't you try it ?
All right , Jason .
The devil worshipers .
The lovers of evil .
It 's a joke .
A pathetic little joke .
We haven 't asked your opinion .
I propose to give it to you anyway .
You 're a poor , wretched group of people who have ...
taken the wrong turning .
Wrong ?
Who knows what is wrong or right ?
If I prefer to believe in satanic majesty and power ,
who can deny me ?
What proof can you bring that good is superior to evil ?
It 's hard to put into words .
But you 're wrong .
One proof .
I 'll prove you wrong .
This afternoon , Jason and I were talking together ,
and I remembered certain phrases from childhood .
Simple , half-forgotten words .
It was the Lord 's Prayer .
I 'm a physician , yet not I nor any of my colleagues ,
no matter how learned ,
ever found a substitute for those few words
as a rule for human relationship .
You might remember them .
" Forgive us our trespasses ,
as we forgive those who trespass against us . "
There 's a sentence for you people from that same prayer .
" Lead us not into temptation , but deliver us from evil . "
All right . Thank you very much .
That was Dr. Judd , Mary .
He phoned to say Jacqueline 's on her way here .
- Gregory . - Yes ?
You 'd better take Jacqueline with you tonight .
It 's what I should have done yesterday .
I 'll take her away someplace where she can rest .
Mary .
No . Stay nearby . I want to talk to you .
I love you .
- You know that ? - Yes .
I 've never loved anyone before , Gregory , and I do love you .
You must know that .
But Jacqueline 's my sister ,
whom I 'd lost and found again .
I know .
I shouldn 't have told you .
No . I 'm glad .
At least I 've heard you say it .
I run to death ,
and death meets me as fast .
And all my pleasures are like yesterday .